<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copie of a certaine letter written by a person of reputation, to a prelate of brabant, being at Brussels. The 25. of Februarie. 1599</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108264</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843934</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8701</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8701)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 523:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copie of a certaine letter written by a person of reputation, to a prelate of brabant, being at Brussels. The 25. of Februarie. 1599</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [E. Allde for] Iohn Wolfe, and are to be solde at his shop in Popes-head Alley neere to the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"Regarding Philip III's gift of the Spanish Netherlands and Brabant to Archduke Albert and Princess Isabella."--STC.</note>
                  <note>A translation form the original Dutch.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8701:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A COPIE OF A CERTAINE LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER WRITTEN BY A perſon of reputation, to a Prelate <hi>of Brabant, being at Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 25. of Februarie. 1599.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe, and are <gap reason="illegible" extent="8 words">
                  <desc>〈8 words〉</desc>
               </gap>-Alley, n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the E<gap reason="illegible" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ge. 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8701:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8701:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ouing Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>the Coppie of this Letter, beeing come to my hands, with the Annotations vppon the gifte or yeelding vp of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlandes, to the Infanta of Spaine, which in my opinion, is not to he ſmothered in obſcuritie, I thought good to put the ſame in Print, to the ende that all louers of the Netherlandish rights and priuileges, may the better vnderſtand (what by the vertuous Catholiques them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues is cenſured of theſe Spanish dealings.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:8701:3"/>
            <head>A copie of a certaine letter, written <hi>by a perſon of reputation, to a prelate</hi> of Brabant, being at Bruſſels.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The 25. of Februarie 1599.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorable, noble, high learned, wiſe, prudent, and moſt diſcreete Lorde.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I haue receiued your letters, dated in Bruſſels the xvi. of Nouember laſt, with the incloſed copie of the gift of the deceaſed king of Spaine, to the noble princeſſe <hi>Iſabella Clara Eugenia,</hi> his eldeſt daughter: of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and the Countrie of Burgundie, in reſpect of the marriage betweene the aboue named illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious princeſſe, and the illuſtrious Prince <hi>Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> Archeduke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> hir coſin, with your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that I should ſincerely wright vnto you my opinion thereof: to wit, vvhether according to my iudgement and feeling, the ſame be a meete meanes to quenche the Netherlandish warres, and to reduce them to a quiet and peaceable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: wherevpon I haue at diuers times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, and notwithſtanding that I haue been in great ſuſpence, in vvhat ſorte and what imported, to giue my iudgement and aduiſe in ſo weighty a matter: yet in reſpect of the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb facs="tcp:8701:3"/>
I owe to your honor, I haue been forced to reſolue &amp; to accomplish your wil vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſure truſt, that this my advice should remaine betvveene vs, and not to bewled to the hinderance and ſcandall of other I cannot bide from your honor, but that vpon this matter in the laſt moneth, diuers aduiſes haue bin ſent me, aſwell out of England, France, &amp; Germany, as out of ſome quarters of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, vvherof ſome are of this opinion, and other of other, that the deceaſed king conſide ring his great age and deſiring to leaue his ſonne, the new <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing a peaceable eſtate, should haue faithfully and in good meaning proceeded herein: other that it is without any apperanne that the Spanish cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell should as any time find good indue meaning to ſeuer the Netherlands from Spaine, as hauing more commodities requiſite to the greatneſſe of a Prince, then all the realines of Spaine, &amp; that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid dealings did onlie tend and ſtretche to attaine and being that to paſſe, vvhich by armes or other means can hardly be done. Beſides that, a certaine perſon of no ſmaſcredit vvith the great, writeth, in confirmation of this laſt opinion, to knovv certainly, that by the high borne Princeſſe &amp; Prince, counter letters should haue been giuen. And alſo that for ſecuritie of their promiſes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:8701:4"/>of it is agreed, that foure of the cheefeſt places of the Netherlands should remaine in the poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spaniards. But without, to build vppon any foundations of theſe deuiſes, I will onely by manner of a gloſe, coate what I finde to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, and finallie to ſet downe my feeling, to vnderſtand the true ground thereof, hoping that your honour the better will conſider in what ſort ought to be dealed for the common quietneſſe &amp; tranquillitie, vnion and wel fare of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and to bring and maintaine them in their olde right ſplender, reſpect and proſperitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching your honor, according to your wiſdom and bountifull diſcretion, to vnderſtand and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the whole to the beſt: and the Lord God Almightie preſerue your honour able, noble, high learned, wiſe, prouident, and moſt diſcreet Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, in a long and proſperous gouernement.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Written the 25. of Februarie. 1599.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Your Honors moſt humble ſeruant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Superſcription.<lb/>
               <hi>To the honorable, noble, high learned,</hi> wiſe, prouident and moſt diſcreet Lorde, Abbot of Saint, &amp;c.<lb/>
At B<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſels.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:8701:4"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Phillip Rex.</signed> 
               <salute>To all preſent and to come which ſhall ſee or heare theſe letters: greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas wee haue found to be moſt be hooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full not onely to our Prouinces of the Low-countries, but alſo, vnto<note n="a" place="margin">I wiſh that this Preface were ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and with words more pleaſing to the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, &amp; tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that which the K of Spaine ſaieth of the great deſire and care hee hath for all Chriſtendo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I doubt that our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour but too much by the former and preſent actes, to ſhewe the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> all Chriſtendome in generall,<note n="b" place="margin">The reaſons of no longer to deferre or delay the marriage (beeing now well neere come to that age, that there is little appearance of hauing children, falleth alſo not well, not yet the Popes holineſſe diſpenſation, to giue the high aboue named Infanta, to his Brother, Nephewe, or Coſin, cannot be very pleaſing.</note> no longer to delay the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of our deare and eldeſt daughter the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta, <hi>Iſabell Clara Eugenia,</hi> being mooued therevnto, as well for the conſeruation of our houſe, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other good reſpects: as alſo, for the great gogd affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which we beare vnto our beloued Brother, Nephewe, and Coſine, the Archouke <hi>Albert,</hi> (at this preſent) Liefte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Gouernour, and Captaine generall, for vs in our Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands and Burgondie: we haue caſt our eyes on him, and chuſing him for the future huſband of our ſaide Eldeſt Daughter, the whole, as well with the conſent and pleaſure of our holy father the Pope, who condiſcendeth, and graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the diſpenſations therevnto belonging, as alſo with the agreement and conſent, of the moſt high, excellent, and puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Prince, our beloued Brother, Nephew, and Coſin, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph,</hi> the ſecond of that name, Emperour of the Romains,
<pb facs="tcp:8701:5"/>
togither with our welbeloued ſiſter the Empres his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>other, which being conſidered, and to the end that our ſaid daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter might bee furniſhed with reaſonable meanes, ſuch as are required for her great calling and merits. Alſo to ſhewe and make known,<note n="(c)" place="margin">I feare that againſt this ſingular and eſpecial loue will be obiected the deaths of the knights of the fleece, many No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen and Gentlemen and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Netherla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, by thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds which haue by violent means, and againſt the rights and priuiledges of the countries.</note> the loue which we haue and doo beer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, vnto our ſaide Netherlands and Burgundie, we haue reſolued (to the aduancement of the ſaid marriage) to<note n="(d)" place="margin">I foreſee, That it will be ſaide that this griefe doth not agree with the generall and particular fights of the Netherlands, in ſuch ſort to giue them in Spaine, but that the one ought firſt to haue beene lawfully aſſembled, the States general and particular of the Prouinces of the Netherlands, to conſider duly all the members, if the ſame ought for the good of the countries to bee permitted, or no: alſo I feare that it will be aſſuredly ſuppoſed and beleeued, that by this gift the Netherlands ſhall ſeeme not by vſurpation, but <hi>quaſi</hi> by their own conſent, to be made ſubiect to the Spaniſh counſels diſpoſition. A matter at times highly deteſted by the Netherlanders, and this opinion, ſhall apparantly be confirmed by ſundrie conditions and reſtraints, contained in this gift, many whereof ſeeme to aſſubiect the Netherlands to Spaine, the which I beleeue will not be ſo vnderſtood nor taken to be either honourable or lawfull to the Netherlanders, not only by the States and Communaltie of the aduerſarie, nor yet by theirs of <hi>Brabant, Flaunders, Haynolt, Artoyes,</hi> and other countries.</note> giue and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port all thoſe ſaid countries, vnto our ſaid Daughter, and all therevnto belonging, in the manner which ſhall be ſpecified here vnder. The whole, with the content and good will, of our deare and welbeloued good ſonne, the Prince <hi>Phillip,</hi> our onely ſonne and heire: according to the aduertiſement, which (by vs and our ſaid ſonne) hath beene giuen vnto the principall Lordes and Knights of our order, Gouernours and Eſtates of our ſaid Netherlands, which are in our obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, togither with thoſe of our countrie of Burgundie. All the which haue witneſſed and declared by their anſwere, the ioy and contentment which they receiued at our ſo kinde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, which they know and confeſſe to bee for the reſt and tranquilitie of our ſaid Netherlands, and that it is the true and right courſe to attaine to a good<note n="(e)" place="margin">I wiſh moreouer, that this deſigne of the kings to ſee the Netherlands in a ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e peace and tranquilitie had been ſoberly rehearſed ſince that the preſent and former proceedinges will bee obiected againſt the ſame, out of which this deſires can hardly be iudged, eſpecially being that fire and ſword, not onely in the Netherlands, but alſo vpon the neutrall neighbors is yet daily as much vſed as euer before. I will not rehearſe the great <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oades and other diſorders committed in the Netherlands on that ſide in this yeare, nor the neuer-to-fore heard mutenies and vnworthie proceedings vpon the caſtle of <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> to the charge and againſt the ſame good Cittie and Cittizens of the Spaniards, alſo the dealings with the Citties of the Empire, <hi>Accken</hi> and <hi>Weſell,</hi> the horrible tyrannie of the land of <hi>Collen, Cleue, Berge, VVeſtphalie, Munſter, Marcke,</hi> and againſt Earles and other perſons, onely I conſider vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the aunſwere of the Admirant <hi>D'arragon,</hi> who being ſhewed and tolde of the Archbiſhops promiſes, ſaith, that <hi>Gods ſeruice and the kings, permit him not to his faith,</hi> which will bee eſteemed farre woorſe then the former, to wit, <hi>That no faith neede be held to Heretickes:</hi> and I am ſorrie that with ſo ſmall conſideration, by the abouenamed Lord Admirant, is ſpoken and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Empires members, that he onely deſireth to haue the Romiſh reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by them maintained and excerciſed, with the depoſing as well with the <hi>Lutherian</hi> as the <hi>Caluian</hi> doctrine, fearing that ſame wil breed a great ſcandal to the Kings, Electors, Princes, and other not vſing the Romiſh religion.</note> and a firme peace, and
<pb facs="tcp:8701:5"/>and to be deliuered from ſuch a troubleſome warre: which quiet and tranquilitie, we haue alwaies wiſhed vnto them.<note n="(f)" place="margin">It beeing true, that the greateſt felicitie which maye happen to a countrie, is to haue a good &amp; wiſe Prince, and to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of him in perſon, vndoubtedly by the aduerſe partie herevpon will be alleaged, that the deceaſed king deſired not the felicitie of the Netherlandes, as not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed, in the ſpace of fortie yeares once to ſee them, but chuſe rather by the Duke of <hi>Alba,</hi> and other his Tyrants, with outlandiſh meane of warre, enemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to inuade the ſame, to holde the Netherlands as a new conqueſted land, to put to death the chiefe Lords, Nobles, and principall Cittizens louers of the lands, rights and priuiledges, or to banniſh them out of the countrie, and to confiſcate their goods, to vſe the reſt as ſlaues to their tyrannie, to builde caſtles in their chiefe citties, to fill them with Spaniſh ſouldiers, to ſet vp and erect new and neuer to ſore heard counſels, againſt the wils of the States of the land, to appoynt and raiſe ſuch contributions as they thought good, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of treating of peace, to ſet abroach newe treaſons, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge in great powers: and in briefe, to reduce the Nethetlandes to ſuch a poynt, that therein they might plant <hi>Sedum belli,</hi> thereby with the countries opportunitie, and good commodities of the riuers, hauens, and ſea holds, the multitude of ſea-faring men and Shippes, togither with the aboundance of all prouiſion needfull to a mightie armie by water and land, to further the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Spaniſh ambition, in the incorporating and eſtabliſhing laws to all Realmes, Countries, and Commonweales, (as they ſay) with the proceeding againſt <hi>Germanie, England, France, Ireland,</hi> and other Realmes and countries manifeſtly ſhew. That the king hath been this fortie yeare ſo buſied with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſuch importance, that he hath not beene able once to ſee the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, (being ſuch worthie, faire, and important countries, which by his Lord and Father, Grandfather, and other his predeceſſors, haue bene helde in ſo high eſteeme) will by many but paſſe for a ſleight excuſe, eſpecially it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwered that his Lord and father the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> only to ſet order in a cauſe of the Cittie of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> not without perill to his perſon, came our of <hi>Spaine</hi> through <hi>France</hi> into the Netherlands.</note> And conſidering that (which vnto all is moſt manifeſt) the greateſt felicitie which may happen to a countrie, to bee gouerned by the ſight and preſence of their naturall Prince and Lord, God is witneſſe of the trouble and care which we haue had, becauſe we haue not bene able in that ſort to doo it perſonally, as (truly) wee well wiſhed, if other great &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant affaires of our Realme of <hi>Spaine,</hi> had not forced and conſtrained vs to make a continuall reſidence therein, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out moouing any thing from thence, as alſo at this preſent they conſtraine vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8701:6"/>
And although the age of our ſaid ſonne, ſeeme more fitte to trauell then doth ours, notwithſtanding it hath beene the pleaſure of the Almightie, to giue ſo many other kingdomes and Countries, for the good gouernment of which, there wil neuer want offaires of great importance, for the which alſo his pretence ſhall here be néedful. We haue then found moſt conuenient to take this reſolution to the ende that our ſaide Low countries be not left in the forepaſſed inconueniences, togither with the reaſon that we haue to appoynt the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſaid daughter the Infanta according to her merits, and the<note n="(g)" place="margin">If the highnes of the birth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> illuſtrious Infanta, or her great merits oght to giue her the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then (might be ſaid), Haue they not beene furthered vnto the ſtates, being lawful<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y aſſembled, pure, cleare and without any conditions ſide commiſſions, or <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrainctions, for all the conditions and reſtraints, will be adiudged to be traps and deceites, therby (according to the doctrine of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he doctors of Tyr<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o) <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng that to paſſe vnder the vaile of a Foxes skinne, which could not be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>l with Lyons cl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes.</note> greatneſſe of her birth.</p>
            <p>As alſo perticularly, that next vnto the ſaid Prince <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:8701:6"/>(vnto whom God confirme with long yeares and proſperitie to his ſeruice) our ſaid eldeſt daughter is the firſt and neereſt heire vnto the ſaid Countries, and therefore, by vertue of the will and pleaſure of our ſaid Sonne, ſhe may from this time be conſtituted in the ſame. The more becauſe wee haue choſe theſe meanes, hoping that thereby our ſaid Netherlands may returne, to their auncient flower, reſt, and proſperitie, which heretofore they haue had.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore we make knowne,</hi> That deſiring at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to put in execution, that whereon we haue ſo ripely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and in reſpect of the voluntarie conſent, which our ſaid Sonne the Prince hath ſo liberally giuen therevnto, after her had vnderſtood, the<note n="(b)" place="margin">It is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that herein they haue vſed the woorde ſubmiſſion ſince that vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it will bee ſaved not to bee ſtraunge, though the ſtates of the Prouinces ſything and panting vnder the Spaniſh tyrannie, ſeeing the Citties enuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, their countries ſuppreſſed with Spaniards, and other outlandiſh ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and the whole and entire gouernment of countries and citties, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded according to the Spaniſh wil: of many miſchiefs, were ſain to chuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, a&amp; that they therfore theron haue bin compelled to ſubmit &amp; yeald the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the Spaniſh Councels will and pleaſure, and to accept the propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conditions. how vnreaſonable burthenſome and vnworthie ſoeuer they ſeemd, but it will neuer bee beleeued, that neither the States nor the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munaltie, which by the ſtaes are repreſented, beeing in libertie, will keepe thoſe forced conditions.</note> ſubmiſſion where with our ſaid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, did confirme our will and intention, wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued and decréed, to <hi>cede</hi> and tranſport to our ſaid Daughter the Infanta, and to the aduancement of the ſaid marriage, all our ſaid Prouinces of the Netherlands &amp; Burgundie, in the forme, manner, and conditions here vnder expreſſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:8701:7"/>
            <head>The conditions wherevpon theſe <hi>anſwers are written, are to be found</hi> in the Booke before Printed, intituled, <hi>The tranſportation of the Lowe Countries, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the firſt condition.</label>
BY this firſt and many other articles, the intent of the Spaniſh king is but too cleare, and the Spaniſh counſaile manifeſt, to wit, that by all meanes they will not onely haue the Netherlands ioyned to Spaine, but eſpecially, that by this gift and tranſport, as with the conſent of the lands, they ſhall be aſſubiected to the Spaniſh gouernment, in ſtéed that vntill now they haue deſtred to vſurpe the ſame by vniuſt and falſe titles.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the third condition.</label>
I haue conſidered vpon the contents of this third article, to wit, that the Archeduke dying without leauing childe or children, procreated by the high borne Infanta: in ſuch caſe this gift ſhall be nothing, and of no worth, and that ſhe inſtéed of theſe Netherlands, ſhall haue her lawfull portion. Héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon will be ſaid, that it is a fit meanes to holde the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands combuſtion, being that no bodie ſhould be able to make the legitimate portion of all the realmes and countries poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by the King of Spaine, aſwell in Europe, as the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, that this catch bringeth with it the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid Spaniſh enterpriſe, to get the Netherlands in their clawes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the fourth condition.</label>
That word, returne to the king of Spaine, ſet in this fourth Article, manifeſteth likewiſe the ſelfe ſame intent.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the fift condition.</label>
By this fift Article appeareth vnreplicably, that at leaſt the Princes of the Netherlands, ſhould for euer remaine ſubiects to the king of Spaine and the Spaniſh counſaile, a matter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnworthy not only for the Netherlands, but alſo for
<pb facs="tcp:8701:7"/>the Princes thereof, and truely, the vertue of the ſtates of the Netherlands prouinces of aboue certaine <hi>100.</hi> yeares paſt was ſo great, that ſuch indignitie durſt not haue béene offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the ſixt condition.</label>
By this ſixt Article, is giuen full power to the king of Spaine and the Spaniſh counſaile, that when as the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands ſhould by ſucceſſion fall in a womans hands, to drawe the ſame to Spaine againe, by marriage with the King or Prince of Spaine, or by hinderance thereof, the Spaniards turning ouer the leafe, and inſtéede that Spaine is now by marriage come to the hands of the Princes of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, they will alwayes make the Netherlands fall into the king of Spaine, thereby with a better title of the ſame to rule them to their pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the ſeuenth condition.</label>
The conditions contained in this ſeuenth Article, in more manifeſt ſort explaineth the intent of the Spaniard, willing that the Princes of the Netherlands, neither their ſonnes nor daughters ſhall marry, without the aduiſe and licence from the king of Spaine: In what plainer and manifeſter ſorte might we ſet the Princes and the Netherlands (againſt the right of all peoples and nations) in the Spaniards protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or wardſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the eight condition.</label>
In this eight Article, I haue conſidered the arrogancie of the Spaniards, in forbidding the Inhabitants of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, the traffick and Nauigation of the Eaſt and Weſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, a matter neuer to fore heard of, and againſt the right of all nations. How much differeth this from the furtherance of the welfare, proſperitie, and auncient flouriſh of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands. The greater part of the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, knowne the king of Spaine. What right (I pray you) haue ſhe Spaniards to forbid the Netherlanders, the traffick &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uightion in thoſe parts? What reaſon hath a Prince of the Netherlands (who is bound to his power to further his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, in trade and welfare) to propoſe ſuch vnméete and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable
<pb facs="tcp:8701:8"/>conditions againſt himſelfe and his ſubiects, and to take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to ſet penalties, that the Netherlands in ſuch caſe ſhould be confiſcated and deuolued to the Spaniards: by what title, foundation, or colour, haue the Spaniards <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot ſuch right in the Netherlands? Truly I am of opinion that many thouſands, aſwell Prelates, Lords, Nobles, as vertue us citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens in Brabant, Flaunders, &amp; other countries (as now ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnder the Spaniard) would rather dye for the countries libertie; then for their ſucceſſors, to accept ſuch diſhonorable and vnlawfull conditions, and it is not apparant that any of the other Prouinces would once thinke vpon ſuch intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and diſhoneſt propoſitions.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the ninth condition.</label>
It will be ſaid, that by this ninth article, the right of the States of the land, is contaminated &amp; deminiſhed, vnto whom during the nonage of their Prince or Princeſſe, the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them and the lands (according to their rights) dooth belong. Which rights may not be acquitted and laide aſide, according to the Spaniſh counſels appetite.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the tenth condition.</label>
Vpon this tenth article I am to ſay nothing as touching the Catholick faith, but I doubt that this preciſe condition of taking ſuch an oath as the text ſheweth, &amp; the penaltie of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſion of the proprietie of the lands, ſhalbe thought to tend but little to a peace and quietnes of the Netherlands (for thoſe of <hi>Holland</hi> &amp; <hi>Zealand,</hi> &amp; other vnited Prouinces, will eſteeme the ſaid condition ſuch, as therby is meant, that it is not deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any time they ſhould be conioyned with the other lands, which notwithſtanding (in my opinion) is the onely waye, to bring Netherland out of theſe broiles of the Spaniſh tiranie, &amp; in her olde flouriſh.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the oath.</label>
Nor yet vpon the forme of this Oath, am I to ſay any thing, but I feare, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> wil expound the ſame, that not onely the Prince bindeth himſelfe and his ſucceſſors to the Romiſh religion, without conſidering that the faith is a gift of God, but alſo that he muſt maintaine his ſubiects therein, and therevnto will bring foorth the Spaniſh Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8701:8"/>
               <label>Vpon the 12. condition.</label>
Vpon this. <hi>12.</hi> article I ſay (according to my iudgement) that no ſure peace, loue, nor correſpondence, can be had between the Spaniards and the Princes of the Netherlands, mor no hope thereof, as long while as the ſaid, Spaniards, ſick (in the leaſt) to vſurpe any thing ouer the Netherlanders, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by this guift ſeemeth to be all their pretence.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Vpon the 13. condition.</label>
I am &amp; haue bene offended in the higheſt degree, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by this <hi>13.</hi> article, that theſe Netherlands ſhould be held as a feoffe o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>feoffe to Spaine, and do not thinke that any Netherlander, (not ouer Hiſpaniolized) would finde it good: for that the Princes of the Netherlands which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> certaine hundred yéeres paſt haue alwaies béen ſouer<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> and abſolute Princes, ſhould henceforward <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the king of Spaine, which wil never <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in any true vertuous Netherlanders heart, but vndoubtedly wil be a cauſe that the Hollanders &amp; their aſſociates, will with theſe vndecent &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable conditions, more iuſtifie their cauſes before all the world, then euer to fore, eſpecially with this oportunity by the kings deceaſe, whoſe deceaſe hath diſcharged euery one of all bonds, &amp; their bonds may not be renued, according to rights, priuileges, and cuſtomes of the countrye, without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which they will neuer yéelde to ſuch conditions.</p>
            <p>By this my briefe annotation, your honor may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, what (in my opinion) vpon each point may apparantly be ſaid by the catholikes themſelues, I haue therein roundly and in good meaning executed your honors charge, vpon hope that my writing ſhall not be ſhewed to any, &amp; vpon the ſame hope, I cannot hide from your honor, (that in my minde) this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned gift will not prooue the right means to reduce the Ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in reſt, peace, &amp; proſperitie, but would eſtéeme it more conuenient, that in this oportunitie, &amp; by the kings deceaſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> States of all the Netherlands ſhould take armes againſt the Spaniard &amp; his adherents, therby to compell the ſaid Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, &amp; other ſtrangers to depart the Netherlands, leauing by prouiſion, euery one in his owne in ſuch order touching the religion as otherwiſe, as they are: to the end that the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards &amp; ſtrangers being driuen out of the ſaid lands, &amp; the ſame land, being ſo reduced in their rights, freedomes, &amp; ſecuritie,
<pb facs="tcp:8701:9"/>that as then the Generall States of all the Netherlands, might aſſemble, and by good meanes take aduiſe and reſolue, vpon the points which ſhould tend to a right and true wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, a during and aſſured peace, reſt and vnion of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, which would be a good and conuenient meanes, not onely for the ſeruice of the Netherlands, but alſo for the high aboue named Infanta, and the illuſtrious Archeduke her lord and huſband, which otherwiſe, by this conditioned guifte would holde them in a perpetuall ſlauerie and ſeruitude of the Spaniards. I know that many honeſt perſons of all quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties amongſt you, and alſo amongſt the aduerſaries of the Spaniards vnto which theſe meanes would be hartely plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and truſt that if the ſame were in earneſt and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually by your honor and others, taken in hand, the Almightie God would yeeld his bleſſing thereto.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8701:9"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
